<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Norseman&#39;s</title>
    <link>https://northofthule.github.io/tags/personal/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Norseman&#39;s</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://northofthule.github.io/tags/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Habits</title>
      <link>https://northofthule.github.io/post/habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 23:57:39 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://northofthule.github.io/post/habits/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I have for the last couple of months tracked my habits using &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.isoron.uhabits&#34;&gt;Loop - Habit Tracker&lt;/a&gt; and I think I might have discovered the holy grail of getting anything and everything done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My projects moves forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The house chores have become fun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daily exercises are and stays daily (!!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My biggest realisation is how much fun routine tasks actually become when you track them as a habit. It is rather counter-intuitive that making anything into a habit, an automated daily event, would make anything more fun. The general consensus seems to be the other way around, routine = BORING. But after tried this out I must say it is really the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tracked habit is a driver for motivation. Because you do your habit every day you quickly see results. And by tracking the habit you force yourself to finish your daily challenge. It works because it is a simple carrot and stick system. Failing a habit will make any human feel they screwed up the day. It would be like going to bed without brushing your teeth - disgusting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is my guidelines how to create great habits. Habits should be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;small&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;easy to accomplished&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;repeatable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serve a clear purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important point is to make the habits small and &lt;em&gt;easy to accomplish&lt;/em&gt;. The goal is to design your habits to be so easy that it would be stupid not to do them. They should preferably play in the same easy-to-accomplish-league as turning of the lights before leaving the house or shave in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer the habit to be so easy that you still can accomplish them 11:30pm before going to bed if you forgot during the day. Your small, easy-to-accomplish goals will keep the motivation up when you see the row of successful days accumulate. Remember that this is something you&amp;rsquo;ll have to do every day. If the bar is too high there will come days when you just can&amp;rsquo;t do it. And then you are forced to break your streak and you risk losing motivation and worse give up. Again, compare to brushing your teeth, you probably haven&amp;rsquo;t forgot more than a handful of times in your lifetime.
Aim low and you will reach high!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, very often the biggest problem is to start. But if you made the task really easy or time-boxed it to just 5-15 min the excuses kind of disappear by themselves and often you end up doing much more than your goal suggest. This is very true for my daily habit of cleaning the house. Especially in the beginning of my cleaning habit I felt a strong resistance of do any kind of house chore. But I kept telling myself &lt;em&gt;it is just 15 minutes, I&amp;rsquo;ll just do some vacuum cleaning for today&lt;/em&gt;. And after just a few minutes I&amp;rsquo;m in the flow and not only vacuum clean but fold clothes, wipe the kitchen table, take out the trash or whatever I feel the need to do. And often those 15 minutes turned into 20-30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crazy thing about my cleaning-the-house-habit  is that now, after a few months of tracking my habit, I actually look forward to my daily chore. I even caught myself thinking of tomorrows cleaning with a smile on my face before going to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not to forget - the result. Oh my gosh, the result! I have never had a more sparkling clean home! Having a soap-scenting home have even become an identity marker for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;naming-habits&#34;&gt;Naming habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name of the habit should preferably be the same as the purpose of the habit. It is a lot more motivative to see the goal of the habit than the task that has to be done. For example, naming the habit &lt;em&gt;Cleaning&lt;/em&gt; is not very motivative at all. But the purpose of cleaning is not to clean, but to get a &lt;em&gt;a clean home&lt;/em&gt;, which is a much better name for a habit. Even better would be something like &lt;em&gt;My sparkling clean home&lt;/em&gt;. When naming a habit - go wild! Your habit deserves some pretty adjectives to describe the fantastic results you want to archive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another one of my habits is to practise Mandarin. Naming it &lt;em&gt;Learn Chinese&lt;/em&gt; would, again, not be a good name. Instead I named it to &lt;em&gt;Speak girlfriends language&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s amazing what a good name and girlfriend can do to a man&amp;rsquo;s motivation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>